This is the most famous
true African adventure,
famous because what took place
at Tsavo never happened before.
Colonel John Patterson
was there when it began.
A fine Irish gentleman,
a brilliant engineer.
He was my friend.
My name is Samuel.
I was there.
Remember this...
Even the most impossible parts
of this story really happened.
John Henry Patterson.
I'm Robert Beaumont.
Firm handshake. I like that.
Tells me a lot about you.
Do sit down.
Now, why don't you
tell me about me?
Well, to get you started,
many people fine me handsome
with a wonderful smile.
I'm sure you agree.
Winning personality,
heaps of charm.
My wife is the game player in the family,
sir.
Thank you, gentlemen.
Look at me closely,
Colonel Patterson.
I'm a monster.
My only pleasure is tormenting
those people who work for me.
People like yourself.
Make one mistake,
and I promise you,
I'll make you hate me.
We're in a race,
Colonel,
and the prize
is nothing less
than the continent
of Africa.
We are building the most expensive
and daring railroad in history
for the glorious purpose of
saving Africa from the Africans
and, of course,
to end slavery.
Our competitors are the
Germans and the French.
We are ahead
and we will stay ahead,
provided you do what
I've hired you to do.
Build a bridge
across the River Tsavo
and be finished
in five months.
Can you do that?
I am sure you've
examined my record.
You know I've never
been late on a bridge.
I'm well aware of your distinguished record,
Colonel,
but let me
humbly remind you,
you've never built
in Africa.
I have in India.
Each country presents
its own challenges.
You'll need all your confidence,
I promise you.
I love Africa.
I've always wanted to go there.
And if I may
speak personally,
my wife is having
our firstborn in six months,
and I promised her I'd
be there for the birth,
and I always
keep my word.
Very moving,
Colonel Patterson.
I'm... I'm touched
you...you confided in me,
but I really don't give a shit
about your upcoming litter.
I've made you
with this assignment.
Don't make me break you.
You won't have
the opportunity.
Any other words
of encouragement?
Then I have
a train to catch.
Tell me
about Beaumont.
Does he understand
how brilliant you are?
How lucky he is
to have you?
It was embarrassing.
The man showered me with praise.
Oh, dear. Tsk.
You're getting that
downtrodden look again.
No. No.
I would never have taken
this had we known sooner.
And you would
have been in agony,
and it would have
been my fault.
You've been desperate to
see Africa all your life.
There may be
difficulties.
There will be.
There always are.
Which only means
that our son and I,
note my confidence,
will have an excuse
to come and visit you.
All aboard!
Come along.
Put me on the train.
You go.
Such a gentleman.
I am desperate to see Africa,
but it's just a place.
You build bridges, John.
You have to go
where the rivers are.
Bye.
Colonel Patterson!
No... No, thank you.
Colonel Patterson, yes?
No, thank you.
Welcome to Africa, sir,
and good morning.
Angus Starling.
I am to assist you at Tsavo.
But Beaumont will have
told you that, surely.
No, actually.
He did give me
his monster speech.
That. Oh, I know
Robert seems dreadful,
but once you truly get to know the man,
he's much worse.
And I'm one
of his defenders.
Forget him for now.
Follow me, sir.
It's your first trip
to Africa, yes?
Good, because I've reserved
the best seats on the train.
They're amazing,
aren't they?
You know the most amazing
thing about them?
They sleep only
five minutes a day.
Don't
like them much.
The females are bigger.
Only animals here
like that.
Have to be
or they wouldn't survive
because the males
eat the young.
Anything special
about them?
Well, it's just that they
fart through their mouths.
I bet they don't
kiss very much.
I've lived in Africa
for a year,
and I don't know
what you know.
How long have
you been here?
Just about 24 hours.
But I've been longing
for this all my life.
Welcome to Tsavo.
Samuel!
Samuel's camp liaison,
absolutely indispensable.
He's the only man here
everyone trusts.
Does he speak English?
And very poor French.
Samuel,
Colonel John Patterson.
The bridge builder.
We've been getting ready
for you.
Good. I'd like to
see the bridge site.
I've got some medical
supplies to deliver.
Come along to the hospital
when you're done.
I'll bring him, Angus.
Where are you from,
Samuel?
That way,
beyond those mountains.
I'm from...
Over there.
Everything seems to be
under control.
Thank you.
If it is, it's a miracle.
Why is that?
The truth is,
the workers don't like each other at all.
Obviously, the Africans
hate the Indians,
but the Indians
also hate other Indians.
The Hindus believe
cows are sacred,
while the Muslims
eat the cows.
Do you eat a cow?
Of course.
I've worked with
both Hindu and Muslim.
Perhaps I can help.
You can certainly try.
It won't work.
Nothing works here.
Tsavo is the worst place
in the world.
Advance camp
is across there.
How many workers?
Three thousand men
laying track.
Even though your bridge
is not yet built,
each day they move two
miles further away.
Did it look like this
in your mind?
No.
This is more difficult.
Should be difficult.
What better job in all the
world than build a bridge?
Bring land over water.
Bring worlds together.
Finish your tour?
Is this
mostly malaria?
Yes, but their suffering
is only transitory.
Once they accept God
into their hearts.
That's just
vomitus talk, Mr. Starling.
Poor bastards will get even
sicker if you don't shut up.
David Hawthorne.
I'm, um...
This is my hospital.
And my advice
to you is...
Don't get sick.
That was meant
to be charming.
Sorry. I seem to
have lost the knack.
You never had it.
Angus and I don't
like each other much.
I am also a liaison
between these two.
Clearly, you don't share
Beaumont's vision.
This? This is a sham.
Who needs it?
It's ridiculous.
It's only being built to
protect the ivory trade,
make rich men richer.
Then why stay, Doctor?
Who else would hire me?
Beat you to it, didn't I?
Dr. Hawthorne...
Oh, yes.
I almost forgot.
You seem to have brought bad luck with you.
Come here.
This is Karim,
one of my orderlies.
He was attacked by a
man-eater earlier today.
A man-eater attacks,
and you're such a buffoon,
you almost forget to mention it.
His injuries
are only slight.
Been riding his donkey
not far from here,
when suddenly
a lion sprang on them.
Donkey took the brunt of it,
then the lion ran off.
Thank you, Karim.
Now, I know this is
your first day,
and you must be tired.
But, um...
What are you going
to do about it?
With any luck,
I'll sort it out this evening.
I don't suppose
I could come and watch?
Have you ever hunted?
Well, not exactly.
I've never been
very adventurous.
Can you keep quiet?
I hate to be a bother,
John, but...
The cramp
is getting worse.
The pain is actually
quite unbearable now.
You'll just have to
cope with it, Angus.
That is precisely my plan.
But back at my tent.
You'll be dead before
you even get to your tent.
The lion will eat you.
I know.
Is this the best way
to hunt a lion?
I don't know.
I've never even seen one.
No!
One shot!
Patterson has made
the night safe again!
My God,
you sorted it out.
There is nothing like
the fear a man-eater brings.
They own the night
and kill so quickly.
It was clear to the men that Patterson
was willing to take risks for them.
That one shot
had taken their fears away.
All right, Angus.
I've decided to have you and Mahina
oversee the foundation piers.
Of course,
the hardest part about building a bridge
is the foundation piers,
and for that task,
I'm giving you
four thrilling weeks.
Aren't we full
of ourselves today?
I think it's
because of the lion.
Uh, John, you know,
I also have killed a lion.
How many shots
did you need?
I used my hands.
Oh.
Uh, John, four weeks
is just not enough time.
You'll just have to
use your hands.
Hey, Samuel!
Come in.
One shot.
The claws of
the lion you killed.
Thank you.
It will always
remind me of Africa.
It is meant to remind you
of courage.
It will also protect you.
Wear it.
"Darling,
"you know how God invented liquor so
the Irish wouldn't rule the world?
"Well, I sometimes think
he invented being bullheaded
"so we could be
the best at something,
"for when this bridge
is finished,
"it will have nothing to do
with my engineering skill
"and all to do
with my stubbornness.
"Africa...
"It changes
everything I plan,
"yet still we are somehow
ahead of schedule.
"Mahina, my foreman,
deserves so much credit.
"The man is a marvel.
"Oh, another marvel.
"Starling has actually convinced
some of the natives to convert.
"I cannot wait to show
this beautiful country to you.
"Love, John."
Simba! Simba!
What the lion
must have done
was lick his skin off
so he could drink his blood.
Then he feasted on him,
starting with his feet.
Lions don't eat this way.
Are you sure this was a lion?
We followed his tracks.
What sort of lion could carry
off someone Mahina's size?
Terror had now built a home
inside us and would not leave,
because if Mahina, who was so powerful,
could not save himself,
what could
the rest of us do?
* Toora loo, toora lay
* Oh, it's six miles
from Bangor to Donaghadee
* Toora loo, toora lay
* Oh, it's six miles
from Bangor to Donaghadee *
You want us to work even if
we have to die to do it!
Why is there
no work being done?
Malaria epidemic.
Very sudden.
There is no reason
for fear.
On that I choose
to remain dubious.
Two are dead now
in two nights.
A second?
Far end of the camp.
A man wandering
alone at night.
There's even less of him
than there was of Mahina.
It's too soon for a lion
to kill from hunger.
In our village, we construct thorn-bush
fences around where we live.
Big burning fires at night.
That keeps the lion away.
Good. Get started.
And a strict curfew.
No one is allowed out
of their tent at night.
Abdullah, you'll send half your men
with Samuel to help build these fences.
The other half
you'll take to the bridge.
Now, I'll sort this out.
I will kill the lion,
and I will build the bridge.
Of course you will.
You are white.
You can do anything.
It would be a mistake not to work
together on this thing, Abdullah.
No! It's got
to be tighter!
You see? This has
got to be a wall!
What a good week.
You mean nobody died?
Well, we all worked together.
Worthy deeds
were accomplished.
I like the labor.
My mother insisted
on piano lessons.
Broke the dear woman's heart when
it turned out I was tone-deaf,
but she was always on at me
to be careful with my hands.
I like the blood.
Is that so strange?
No.
Oh, yes. I think so.
Here it comes, Samuel.
Even you two must admit it is
glorious what man can accomplish.
With one common splendid goal,
there are no limits.
Think what will be done when we all
have God's warmth in our hearts.
I am immune
to your disdain.
When I came here,
I had one small goal,
to convert the entire
continent of Africa.
Now I've decided to move on to
something really difficult.
I will not rest until both of
you are safely in the fold.
I'm beyond conversion.
My mother's
Roman Catholic,
and my father's
a Protestant.
I have four wives.
Good luck.
The struggle
is the glory.
For you.
Thank you, Samuel.
Good news.
I expect so...
From my wife.
You like her?
Very much.
I don't like any of mine.
"Darling,
the big excitement yesterday
"was when some schoolchildren
spotted a whale.
"They were
looking at me, John.
"That was an attempt at humor,
but I don't feel very funny these days.
"Anyway, after our son,
"you'll note I still have
total confidence,
"well, after he's born,
I think travel might be the order of the day.
"As he kicks me at night,
I'm quite sure he's telling me
"he definitely
wants to come to Africa.
"Thought you might
need reminding."
Move! Move yourselves! Move!
Angus! Stay here.
Oh, God!
Jesus.
There are two of them.
Oh, Jesus.
"And the king spake
and said unto Daniel,
"'Oh, Daniel, servant
of the living God,
"'is thy God, whom thou
servest continually,
"'able to deliver thee
from the lions?'
"And Daniel said unto the king,
'Oh, king, live forever.
"'My God hath sent his angels
and hath shut the lions' mouths
"'that they
have not hurt me,
"'for as much as before him,
innocency was found in me.
"'And as before thee, oh,
king, have I done no hurt.
"'Have I done no hurt.'"
The men called them
the Ghost and the Darkness.
There were two of them,
and that had never
happened before
because man-eaters
are always alone.
They owned the nights,
but they also
attacked in daylight,
alone or together,
without fear or reason.
Some thought
they were not lions at all,
but the spirits of dead medicine
men come back to spread madness.
For others,
they were the devil,
sent to stop the white men
from owning the world.
I believed this,
that they were evil,
and what better ground
for evil to walk than Tsavo?
Because this is what
the word "Tsavo" means,
a place of slaughter.
I've given you my word.
Why haven't you told them help is on the way?
It's too late now,
Mr. Patterson.
It's not too late. Abdullah, they will
listen to you. You must make them stay.
They are too afraid to work.
They want to go home.
Be content that
I have decided to stay.
Beaumont is
on that train.
If he sees this mess,
you will lose your job.
So will you, sir.
That's all, really, you care about.
Oh, for Christ...
Well, then, you go, too.
You lack
the courage to lead.
Go. Tell all
of your men to go,
but I will kill the lions,
and I will
build the bridge,
and you, you must go home
and tell the wives of the men
who died working here
that you fled with the others because
you could not master your fear.
Welcome to Tsavo.
Pleasant journey?
How could it be?
I hate Africa.
That's a lovely sound.
They seem happy.
Don't they, though?
So, work's going well?
What of my request
for soldiers?
I told you before.
You're on your own.
There will be
no soldiers here.
I promised
my men protection.
Where's Starling?
A while back,
he ordered some Bibles.
I've brought them.
Is he here?
Where is he?
Where's Starling?
Here he comes.
What happened?
I'll show you.
Nothing wrong
with these people.
They're afraid.
What the hell
is going on?
The Ghost and the Darkness
have come.
In English.
It's what the natives
are calling the lions.
There's a legend here.
Two man-eaters are making all the trouble.
Well, this is Africa, Patterson.
I thought you were a hunter.
It's not that simple.
These lions are...
Not like lions.
How many have they killed?
About 30,
I should think.
Christ!
You've been here three months,
and already you're behind schedule.
Don't you know that the French and
the Germans are right behind you?
And I don't care
about you,
and I don't care
about the 30 dead.
I care about
my knighthood.
As to your request
for troops,
do we wish the world to think that
the builders of the British Empire
are afraid
to do their job
because of a few minor difficulties
with the local wildlife?
I don't think so.
So, what are you
planning to do?
I'm calling it
my contraption.
I placed it here because
this is the area of the camp
where the lions
have attacked the most.
I'm surrounding it
with a boma...
What?
A fence.
Except for this small area
here opposite this door.
Just what kind of lunacy are
we dealing with here? Hmm?
On the other side of these bars will be bait,
human bait.
I'll start things off.
About here will be a tripwire
for this sliding door.
Genius!
The beast will enter,
tripping the wire,
the door will slide down
behind him, trapping him.
You, meanwhile,
safe behind your bars,
will have the beast
at your mercy
and will shoot him
at your leisure.
Are you running
a high fever, man?
How could you conceive of
something so idiotic?
I didn't conceive of it
for the lions.
It was for a tiger
in India.
And it worked?
In point of fact, it didn't,
but I'm convinced
the theory is sound.
I made a mistake
hiring you, Patterson.
The world is watching us.
I need initiative,
not contraptions.
I need a professional hunter.
I'm going to
locate Remington.
I assume
you've heard of him.
Every man who's ever
hunted has heard of him.
I wish he were
here right now,
but by the time
you find him,
the lions will be dead,
and I'll be back on schedule.
All right,
the job's still yours,
but only because it would take
too long to find a replacement.
I'll go, but if I have to return,
you're finished.
I will then do everything
within my considerable power
to destroy
your reputation.
Fair enough?
I told you
you'd hate me.
"Helena, everything
is collapsing on me.
"Every morning, the ground
is soaked with blood.
"The workers feel
I brought this terror
"since it didn't begin
till my arrival.
"Whatever I try,
they seem to know.
"All the deaths are on me."
Very good.
Very impressive.
We've been hunting
since childhood.
You're murderers,
criminals...
That's good.
You'll be spending
your nights in there,
and of course, you'll have
nothing to fear.
That is correct.
Nothing.
Fire! Fire!
Fire!
Of course he kept moving!
What did you want him to do,
sit down and pose for you?
Now, this worked.
He came in, hit the wire.
He couldn't have been more than 15
feet away from the three of you,
and you couldn't
even wound it!
Should have given you rocks,
not rifles.
There is not a trace
of blood anywhere.
This is insane.
I assure you,
we came close many times.
There must be blood.
The next time
will be better!
Next time will be
as this time!
The devil has
come to Tsavo!
That's ridiculous talk,
and you don't really believe it.
Now you are telling me
my beliefs?
I don't think so!
I wasn't, and you know it,
so don't force it.
Listen, we do
have a problem in Tsavo.
At last, finally we agree.
You are right. We do!
We do! You are
the problem in Tsavo!
He is the problem
in Tsavo!
You listen...
Be careful!
You don't tell me careful.
You don't
tell me anything!
We are sick
and tired of your lies!
You listen while I talk!
Change in plans.
Get them back!
Now, get them all back!
Go back!
Quickly, go back!
Go back! Go back!
Go back!
All right,
you listen while I talk
because you got a question
needs answering.
Will I pull this trigger?
You don't know all
that has happened here.
He will pull
the trigger, Abdullah.
The devil has
come to Tsavo!
Oh, you're right.
The devil has come to Tsavo.
Look at me!
I am the devil.
I'm a man of peace!
You sound like a man
who wants to live.
Most certainly.
Absolutely. Yes.
Well, that's
an excellent decision.
Your name is Abdullah.
Yes.
Well, I'm sure we're
going to meet again.
I think it's been a pleasure.
John Patterson.
Aye.
Remington uses
the Maasai to hunt lions.
It will cost you
10 head of cattle.
He takes some
getting used to.
Why didn't you tell me
you knew him?
You did not ask.
I didn't get a chance
to thank you.
For what? What did I do?
Got me
out of trouble.
Oh, that was nothing.
Samuel was there.
He would have
done something.
What was that
all about, anyway?
There are
over 40 dead.
Forty? That's amazing.
There's a few things you
should know about these lions.
Let me save you
some time.
Now, you're the engineer,
and you're in charge of building the bridge.
Am I right so far?
That's right.
All right, I am not an engineer,
and I don't want to be in
charge of building that bridge.
That's fine.
Now, I'm sure you probably
hate Tsavo as much as I do,
and knowing Beaumont,
you're not the imbecile that he says you are.
So what do you say
we help each other?
Now, I'm going
to help you
by killing the lions
and then leaving,
and you're
going to help me
by doing what I say
so I can leave.
You see a problem
with that?
Actually, no.
Let us prepare for battle.
Whew!
All right...
First thing I'm going to propose
is a new hospital, all right?
And I want it built
by tomorrow night.
What?
That's a terrible idea.
Oh, I'm sorry. You must
be the doctor, right?
I'm sure
you know what's best.
That's the most infantile thing
I've ever heard in my life.
Now, whoever you are,
will you mind telling me
why on earth we should
go through all that?
I suppose I could explain what,
with the scent of flesh and blood in here,
it makes for
an inviting target.
I suppose I could tell you I just
saw fresh paw prints out there
which make me think they're already
thinking about feasting in here,
but I don't want to answer you
because when you question me,
you are saying to me that I
don't know what I'm doing.
Now, anybody here think I'm a fool,
then please speak up right now.
Colonel Patterson...
Well, then I guess
we all agree.
I'm going to need you
there with me tomorrow.
Whatever you wish.
Samuel says
you killed a lion.
It was probably just luck.
Oh, nobody kills a lion
with one shot by luck.
You might be useful
tomorrow.
But even if you're not,
you should understand
this may take me two,
maybe three days to sort this out.
But when I leave,
you're still going to have
to build that bridge,
so I don't want your men
to lose respect for you.
That's very considerate
of you.
Well, I'm a very
considerate man.
My mother taught me that.
Now, what the hell
are you laughing about?
You don't think
I'm considerate?
I don't believe
you had a mother.
You really believe you can
make something happen...
Hmm?
But you're not excited.
You don't enjoy
killing, do you?
Then why do it?
Because I've got a gift.
I'm going
to join them now.
We could try to convince each
other that we're still brave.
I wouldn't have thought bravery
would be a problem for you.
Well,
you hope each time it won't be...
But you never
really know.
Strange man.
Two great tribes
of his country
fought a terrible
civil war for many years.
And his side lost?
Everything.
Land and family.
Very young ones
and the very old ones...
All lost.
He buried his family
and left his country forever.
Now he hunts
all over the world,
but he always
returns here.
He says Africa
is the last good place.
John?
Will you exchange
weapons with me?
Mine's much more powerful.
I won't be with you tomorrow.
I'll be finishing
the new hospital.
Thank you.
Why does he need you with him?
He doesn't.
We've hunted many times.
He knows
I'm afraid of lions.
Well, I spotted at least
one of them in the thicket.
Samuel,
you're coming with me.
Chances are I'm going to kill
that lion in the thicket.
Colonel, why don't you take the higher
position there in case he gets through us?
You'll have
a clear shot at him.
Shoot him.
Shoot him!
God damn it! Shoot him!
What happened?
I don't know.
What do you mean you don't know?
Misfire.
That the first time?
The gun belongs
to Dr. Hawthorne.
You exchanged weapons?
You went into battle
with an unproven rifle?
Whew!
They got an expression
in prizefighting.
Everybody's got a plan
until they've been hit.
Well, my friend,
you've just been hit.
The getting up,
that's up to you.
They say
they are leaving now
because it does
no good to be here.
They are not lions.
They are the Ghost and the Darkness.
The Maasai did not see a lion.
They saw the devil.
They knew there was not
enough blood in all the world
to make these demons
stop drinking.
Remington laughed at us.
He said that
they were only lions.
Gentlemen, there is no smell of
sickness and very little blood.
We have removed all of the lions'
temptations.
Now, when we
leave this evening,
I want you to lock this gate
securely until the morning.
Keep those fires burning high.
Are there any questions?
Aren't there
any questions?
All right, you two sleep beautifully
in your tent, and you stay there.
And where will you two
sleep beautifully?
Colonel Patterson and I will spend the
night waiting in the old hospital.
Won't we, Colonel?
And I can assure you,
with the fresh scent of blood,
those lions are going
to find it irresistible.
Just think
about something else.
Have you ever failed?
Only in life.
I meant to ask you,
that trap you set in the boxcar,
was that your idea?
Aye.
Excellent notion.
I used the same device
myself once.
But, of course, yours worked.
No.
No, in point of fact,
it didn't.
It was still a good idea.
Psst! Psst!
Johnny, get the lock.
We must not leave.
That's my hospital,
for God's sake!
We must not leave!
Let me go, Samuel.
Hurry up!
Get on!
Mzee.
One of us
needs to be brave.
Would have been
a beautiful bridge, Johnny.
It's funny how I didn't
notice it before.
I guess I had some other
things on my mind.
It's not actually something
I would appreciate,
except, you know,
I got up this morning, and...
It's just such
a pretty design
and the setting
is so beautiful.
You've just been hit.
Yeah.
The getting up's up to you.
And they're only lions.
Yeah. Yeah, they're
only lions, yeah.
Well, I just saw some fresh paw
prints heading out that way.
So, I guess
we've both been hit.
Let's go after them.
Hey.
Yeah.
Whoo.
Oh, Johnny boy.
When I was growing up,
there was a bully in my hometown.
He used to terrorize
everybody,
but he wasn't
the problem.
He had a brother who
was worse than him,
but he wasn't
the problem either.
One or the other of them
was always in jail.
The problem was when
they were together.
Alone they're just bullies,
but together, whew!
They were lethal.
They were real killers.
What happened to them?
Well, I got bigger.
Oh, my God.
Holy Christ.
Lions don't do this.
Lions never had
a lair like this.
They're doing it
for the pleasure.
They'll know
we've been here.
Oh, my God.
Both of them.
Yeah, it's both of them.
Have you ever
used a machan?
A what?
Machan.
Is that one of those things
you learned in India?
I figure they've got
used to me in trees,
so, if we put this
in a clearing.
I'm not quite sure
of the scale.
It might be too small
for the both of us.
No, it won't because
I ain't gonna be there.
This is your idea.
You get up on that thing.
So, I'm to be bait alone.
That's right. I'm going to be in some
tree too far away to protect you.
Now, can you
control your fear?
I suppose
I'll have to.
Lions hate the sound
of a baboon.
Anything to make your
evening more enjoyable.
Hey, this here's
for you.
You might need it.
Well, this certainly
is the best opportunity
those lions have had
to kill you.
Mzee, good luck.
Including the workers that I've lost
and your knowledge of man-eaters,
how many do you think
they've killed?
Oh, more than
any other lion.
A hundred, maybe more.
But you know something?
I do believe this is going to work.
Why?
Because I think
they're after you.
Oh, merry Christmas.
What?
Oh, yeah.
This is the month.
Son of a bitch.
Ah!
Excuse me.
Why on earth
do you laugh?
Because he is just like
one of those bullies now.
He's alone
for the first time,
and he's afraid.
Somehow I don't think
he's afraid of me.
You know, I just keep wondering if
we're going to remember all this.
I love Africa.
I could never
forget her.
Oh.
Well, you're young,
Johnny.
I mean, so many
things flash by,
and at that moment you say, "Oh, yeah.
This is going to stay with me.
"Surely, I will never
forget this dawn.
"This hunt.
"This passion."
And then...
It's all gone.
But I hope it stays here.
Another toast.
To memory.
I wanted to remember
building the railroad.
The iron snake.
I was so excited.
Now I can't think why.
I know why I wanted
to build the bridge,
but I can tell you
the memory I wanted most.
To see my son
come into the world.
To bring worlds together.
Now, I...
Well, my life was shaped because
someone invented gunpowder,
and that's what took me
around the world.
But the memory
that I wanted...
That was the family
that I lost.
You know, Charles,
you're a rather cheerful fellow
when you get to know you.
Well, I should have
warned you.
Good night.
Oh, Johnny.
When you meet your son,
you hold him high.
Aye.
Excuse me.
I'd like to see
John Patterson, please.
Yes, ma'am.
Could you tell him
that his wife...
That his family
has come to see him?
Sorry.
Hello!
Hello, darling!
No.
Hello.
Helena!
I can see you.
Go back! Go back!
Hello!
No! Go back! Go back!
Go back!
No!
No, Charles.
Oh, God.
Charles!
Mzee.
John!
Where do you think
you're going?
I'm going to sort it out.
I'm going...
...to sort it out.
Get down!
Get down, John!
Down!
John!
Colonel Patterson!
My name is
Nigel Bransford.
I'm here to replace
Angus Starling.
I'm so proud
to meet you.
Patterson the Lion Killer.
I do wish I had been
here for the hunt.
No, you don't.
John.
Mmm-hmm.
Welcome to Tsavo, Nigel.
Patterson
did hold his son high.
People came back.
Patterson
finished the bridge.
People went their ways.
If you want to see
the lions today,
you must go to America.
They are at the Field Museum
in Chicago, Illinois.
Even now, if you dare
lock eyes with them,
you will be afraid.